Hemşelek, qeryetun sûriyyetun cemîle.
Hamshalak, a beautiful Syrian village.
Teqa'u şemal xerb medînet Efrîn bi wahed we 'işrîn
kîlometran.
Located northwest of the city of Afrin by 21 kilometers.
We cenûb medînet Raco bi sitte kîlometrat.
And south of the city of Rajo by 6 kilometers.
We şemal xerb medînet Heleb bi semanin kîlometran.
And northwest of the city of Aleppo by 80 kilometers.
Îla e-şemal minha teqa'u Raco, kema enne îla el-cenûb teqa'u
nahiyet Ma'betlî.
To the north of it lies Rajo, as to the south lies the sub-
district of Ma'batli.
We şerqen qeryet Birbend we sikket hedîd e-şerq e-serî'.
And to the east the village of Birband and the fast east
railway.
Emma xerben fa beldet Ba'denlî.
While to the west is the town of Ba'danli.
El-qerye el-qedîme teqa'u e'la el-qerye el-haliye.
The old village is located above the current village.
We qad hacereha ehluha fî el-rub' e-sanî min el-qern
el-'işrîn.
And its people migrated from it in the second quarter of the
twentieth century.
Bi sebeb wu'ûret e-terîq el-wasil îleyha.
Due to the ruggedness of the road leading to it.
We kanet mu'ellefe min selaset tecemmu'at sekeniye
mutecawire qurbe qummet el-cebel.
And it consisted of three adjacent residential gatherings
near the mountain peak.
'Umr el-qerye el-haliye la yezîdu 'an selase mi'et 'am.
The age of the current village does not exceed 300 years.
We sukkanuha el-ewa'il min el-ekrad e-sûriyyîn el-lezîne
yentemûn îla 'eşîret Bîyan el-kurdiye.
And its first inhabitants are Syrian Kurds who belong to the
Kurdish Biyan tribe.
We min el-'ereb el-lezîne yentemûn îla 'eşîret En-Ne'îm
el-'erebiye.
And Arabs who belong to the Arab Al-Naim tribe.
Yeskunu fîha haliyen hawalî selase mi'et 'a'île min
sukkaniha el-esliyyîn.
Currently, about 300 families of its original inhabitants
live in it.
We min 'ewa'il muhecere qesren min menatiq Sûriye muxtelife.
As well as forcibly displaced families from different Syrian
regions.
Ye'temidu ehluha fî heyatihim 'ela e-zira'e we terbiyet el-
heywanat.
Its people rely in their lives on agriculture and animal
husbandry.
We 'ela el-mebalix el-maliye el-letî yuhawwiluha lehum
ebna'uhum fî el-mehcer.
And on the financial amounts transferred to them by their
children in the diaspora.
Heyse enne nisbeten kebîreten min ebna'iha hacerû îla
Turkiya we Ewropa.
As a large percentage of its children have migrated to
Turkey and Europe.
Yûcedu fî el-qerye medrese îbtida'iyye wahide.
There is one primary school in the village.
We ye'temidu ehluha fî şurbihim 'ela el-abar el-îrtiwaziye
el-mewcûde fî el-qerye.
And its people rely for their drinking on the artesian wells
located in the village.
Ya rab.
Oh Lord.
Selamun aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
We aleykumusselam, ya ehla we sehlen.
And upon you be peace, welcome.
Feyn edxul?
Where do I enter?
Fût.
Enter.
Maşaellah, maşaellah haza 'ineb hilû ktîr.
Mashallah, mashallah, these are very beautiful grapes.
Elhemdulellah, fî fî hey kwayis.
Praise be to God, there is, there are these good ones.
Ya rab.
Oh Lord.
Tefeddel we xud rahitek.
Please come in and make yourself comfortable.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Şlonek?
How are you?
Elhemdulellah, ehlen we sehlen.
Praise be to God, welcome.
Allah yuhyîk. Merheba uxtî.
May God bless you. Hello sister.
Şlonek?
How are you?
Elhemdulellah. Ehlen we sehlen.
Praise be to God. Welcome.
Fîna nibruk şway heyk nihkî şway?
Can we sit a bit and talk a little?
Eyy nibruk, ehlen we sehlen.
Yes we can sit, welcome.
Bişerref.
I'd be honored.
Birkî ya uxtî birkî.
Sit down sister, sit down.
Xellînî axud el-kursî min hon, îrtah hadretek.
Let me take the chair from here, make yourself comfortable.
Îrtah bişerref.
Make yourself comfortable, I'd be honored.
Selametak, ke'ennek merdan?
Feel better, it seems you are sick?
Eyy merdan wellahi.
Yes, sick by God.
Şû sayir me'ak?
What happened with you?
Wellah merrteyn sar celta..
By God, I had a stroke twice..
Selametak ya rabb.
Feel better, oh Lord.
Sawwert sûret renîn bi e-Şam, el-merrteyn derebu celta.
I took an MRI scan in Damascus, both times I was hit by a
stroke.
Selametak ya rabb.
Feel better, oh Lord.
We uzney darimnî keman.
And my ear hurts me too.
Îznek?
Your ear?
Selametak.
Yes.
Feel better.
Îhkî lî 'en heyatikum înti hon, tefaddalî hon şway.
Tell me about your life here, please come here a bit.
Înti zewcetu?
Are you his wife?
Eyy.
Yes.
Nite'erref aleykî şway?
Can we get to know you a bit?
Xedîce Mislim.
Khadija Muslim.
Ya ehla we sehlen fîkî.
Welcome to you.
Ehlen we sehlen fîk.
Welcome to you too.
Şlon heyatikum bi hal dhey'e?
How is your life in this village?
'Adiye heyk.
Just normal.
Nişteğil, fî 'enna 'enzat we heyk şî.
We work, we have goats and things like that.
'Adiye.
Normal.
Ye'nî heyatikum mu'temide 'ela e-zira'e we terbiyet el-
heywanat.
So your life depends on agriculture and animal husbandry.
Eşşû e-zira'e hon?
Yes, by God.
What is the agriculture here?
Zeytûn.
Olives.
Ekter şî bî e-dhey'e zeytûn?
The most common thing in the village is olives?
Eyy.
Yes.
Şû enwa' el-zeytûn?
What are the types of olives?
Ma be'rif.
I don't know.
Zeytî, zeytî...
Zayti, Zayti...
Zeytî 'enna hon...
We have Zayti here...
Fî xelxalî, ma fî heyk, ma fî keza?
Are there Khalkhali, aren't there things like that?
Fî xelxalî, fî ebu şoka...
There is Khalkhali, there is Abu Shoka...
Eyy la' fî fî bî dhey'e fî, fî xelxalî, fî kul şî.
Yes, no, there are in the village, there is Khalkhali, there
is everything.
Eşşû murebbîn heywanat hon 'endekum?
What animals are you raising here?
'Enzat we ğanemat heyk şî.
Goats and sheep and such.
Kem wehde 'endekum?
How many do you have?
Tneyn.
Two.
Tneyn?
Two?
Ma 'endekum ebqar?
Don't you have cows?
La.
No.
Hellaq ena sumi'it inno hon fî 'endekum loz, 'endekum summaq
heyk 'am yahkû.
Now, I heard that you have almonds here, you have sumac,
that's what they say.
Fî ktîr bas 'enna nihne fî zeytûn.
There is a lot, but we have olives.
Bas.
That's all.
Fî bî dhey'e fî kul şî.
There is everything in the village.
Tebî'et el-nas hon şlon?
How is the nature of the people here?
Mnihe kwayyise, elhemdulellah.
Good, fine, praise be to God.
Ye'nî nas besîtîn...
I mean simple people...
Nas mufettehîn...
Open-minded people...
Îhkî lî, se'bîn, sehlîn, şlon?
Tell me, are they difficult, easygoing, how?
Elhemdulellah, maşî halo, kwayis walla.
Praise be to God, things are okay, it's good by God.
Nas kulo kwayis we el-cew kwayis elhemdulellah kwayis.
People are all good and the weather is good, praise be to
God, it's good.
Elhemdulellah, înti şû re'yik?
Praise be to God, what is your opinion?
Kulhum heyk besîtîn qadd halhum heyk.
All of them are simple like this, just getting by.
Elhemdulellah.
Praise be to God.
Eşşû fî 'endekum ewlad?
Do you have children?
Ma 'enna.
We don't.
Ma 'etekum ewlad?
God didn't grant you children?
Allah ma be'etlekum.
God didn't send you any.
Elhemdulellah 'ala kul hal.
Praise be to God in any case.
Ecmel şî bi hal dhey'e eşşû hûwe?
What is the most beautiful thing in this village?
Heyk kil el-..ye'nî nas el-'adiyîn heyk besîtîn, ye'nî kul
şî.
Like this, all the.. I mean ordinary people, simple like
this, I mean everything.
Ma be'rif kul wahid bihib dhey'eto.
I don't know, everyone loves their village.
Teb'en dhey'etkum hilwe.
Of course your village is beautiful.
Hefzane şî heyk mewwal kurdî?
Have you memorized a Kurdish song?
Kelimat, şî heyk...
Words, something like this...
Makî hefzane?
You haven't memorized?
La.
No.
We le înti?
And you?
La.
No.
Lîş?
Why?
Ene ma be'rif 'ala sawtî.
I don't know, my voice...
La ma ba'rif wallahi.
No, I don't know by God.
Allah yu'afîkum.
May God bless you with health.
Şukran îlkum, yu'tîkum el-'afiye.
Thank you, may God give you health.
Ehlen we sehlen fîkum.
Welcome to you.
Ehlen fîkum, Allah yu'afîkum.
Welcome to you too, may God give you health.
Selamun aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Merheba ya sabiye.
Hello young lady.
Şlonek?
How are you?
Temam elhemdulellah.
Fine, praise be to God.
Allah yu'afîkî, mîn hedretik?
May God give you health, who are you?
Huda Malik Ed-Dahûd.
Huda Malik Al-Dahoud.
Ya ehla we sehlen fîkî ya Huda. We înti?
Welcome Huda. And you?
'Abdo, haza exûkî?
Abdo.
Abdo, is this your brother?
Eyy.
Yes.
We haza, e-sebî z-zğîr el-hilû?
And this, the cute little boy?
Mueyyed.
Muayyad.
Mueyyed?
Muayyad?
Eyy.
Yes.
Şû ismik înti?
What is your name?
Îsmî A'îşe e-Dahûd.
My name is Aisha Al-Dahoud.
Ehlen we sehlen bi 'Ayyûş, 'Ayyûş...
Welcome Ayyoush, Ayyoush...
Te'al şûf îtu ixwe?
Come, let's see, are you siblings?
Eyy.
Yes.
Întu min weyn?
Where are you from?
Min e-d-Dibse min Îdlib.
From Al-Dibsa, from Idlib.
We lissa fî exûye bilbeyt.
And there's still my brother at home.
Ehlen we sehlen fîkum.
Welcome to you.
Saknîn hon?
Are you living here?
Eyy.
Yes.
Su'al îtu 'em tudrusu fî l-medrese?
Question, are you studying in school?
La', kinna bilcami' bas batalne.
No, we were at the mosque but we stopped.
Leyş?
Why?
Ma 'em nistefad şî.
We aren't benefiting anything.
Ma 'em tistefîdî şî?
You aren't benefiting anything?
Ye'nî ma derestî fî l-medrese?
I mean, you didn't study in school?
La', ma lehaqna.
No, we didn't catch up.
Ma lehaqtu.
You didn't catch up.
Eşşû hefzane?
What have you memorized?
Şû hinne 'iddî lî ya hum şû.
What are they? Count them for me, let's see.
Elif, ba, ta, sa, cîm, ha...
Alif, ba, ta, tha, jeem, ha...
Ê hefzane.
Yes, you have memorized.
'Ayyûş hefzane.
Ayyoush has memorized.
Teyb e'tînî inşûde...
Ok, give me a song...
İnşûde heyk neşîde...
A song, like a chant...
Di'uqre.. Malik yewm ed-dîn...
Should I recite.. Master of the Day of Judgment...
Ê yella îqre'î.
Yes, go ahead and recite.
Bismillehirrehmanirrehîm. Errahmanirrehîm. Maliki yewmiddîn.
Îyyake ne'budu we îyyake neste'în. Îhdinesiratelmusteqîm.
Siratellezîne en'emte aleyhim xeyrilmeğdûbi aleyhim.
Sadaqallahulel'ezîm.
In the name of God, the Gracious, the Merciful. The
Gracious, the Merciful. Master of the Day of Judgment. It is
You we worship, and upon You we call for help. Guide us to
the straight path. The path of those You have blessed, not
of those against whom there is anger.
Allah yu'tîki l-'afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah yuwaffiqkum ya rab.
May God grant you success, oh Lord.
Ktîr hilwîn îtu heyk ma' ba'ad waqfîn ke'ixwe.
You are very sweet standing together like this as siblings.
Bes 'Ayyûş muctehide ha.
But Ayyoush is hard-working.
Yella, yu'tîkum el-'afiye.
Alright, may God give you health.
Ya rab.
Oh Lord.
Min be'îd left nezerî, selamun aleykum.
From afar it caught my eye, peace be upon you.
Aleykumusselam.
Upon you be peace.
Şlonik?
How are you?
Temam. Elhemdulellah.
Fine. Praise be to God.
Allah yu'afîkî.
May God give you health.
Mîn hedretik?
Who are you?
Min Kufr Emîm.
From Kafr Amim.
Ehlen we sehlen fîkî.
Welcome to you.
Îtle'î şway lifoq?
Can you come up a bit?
Şifna l-bab meftûh, şifna hedretik.. ma t-terîq.. ye'nî
nihkî me'akî.
We saw the door open, we saw you.. on the way.. I mean, to
talk with you.
Eyy ehlen we sehlen, tefaddalû.
Yes, welcome, come in.
Kîf heyatkum? heliktû ma?
How is your life? You're exhausted, right?
La ma helikna.
No, we are not exhausted.
Ma mebruk.. wallahi el-heyat...
There's no sitting.. by God, life...
Wallahi el-heyat mnîhe.
By God, life is good.
Qarrbî hon şway heyk illî biyin dhey'e.
Come closer here a bit, the one who shows the village.
Temam, el-heyat...
Fine, life...
Şlon?
How is it?
Ye'nî 'ayişîn elhemdulellah.
I mean we are living, praise be to God.
Eşşû el-hilû bî hal dhey'e?
What is beautiful in this village?
Nasu wa e-şa'ab.
Its people and the folk.
Şlon îhkî lî 'en e-şa'ab?
How? Tell me about the folk.
Ye'nî wallahi ktîr ekabir.
I mean by God, very noble.
Nihne krad we 'ereb hon 'ayişîn wa muteheccirîn nihne, bas
ktîr ktîr ekrad tayyibîn me'na.
We are Kurds and Arabs living here, and we are displaced,
but the Kurds are very, very kind with us.
Elhemdulellah, bes el-heyat qasiye şway.
Praise be to God, but life is a bit harsh.
Eş nas hon kîf 'ayişîn?
How are the people living here?
'Ayişîn...
Living...
'Am nistenna ferec Allah.
We are waiting for God's relief.
Ye'nî hey e-l-'îşe.
I mean this is the living.
Hey el-'îşe.
This is the living.
Eş 'endik ewlad?
Do you have children?
'Eyiştna saffet heyk, xamse. Tlete sabyan we binteyn.
Our life has become like this, five. Three boys and two
girls.
Allah yuxellîhum.
May God keep them.
'Am yudrusû?
Are they studying?
La.
No.
Ma 'am yudrusû.
They aren't studying.
La.
No.
Eşşû heyk şî te'allemtiye min ha d-dhey'e el-hilwe, 'adat,
teqalîd, qiyam eşşû?
What did you learn from this beautiful village, customs,
traditions, values, what?
Wallahi te'allemne inno nkûn qadd halna.
By God, we learned to be self-reliant.
Fî kuli şî.
In everything.
Ye'nî fî l-herb killiya te'allemne inno nkûn qadd halna.
I mean in the whole war, we learned to be self-reliant.
Ene me'ik, lakin.. el-yewm.. hey d-dhey'e ktîr hilwe, ye'nî
nas besîtîn we tayyibîn.
I am with you, but.. today.. this village is very beautiful,
I mean simple and kind people.
Ye'nî ktîr el-'alem biseba we tayyibîn.
I mean a lot of the people are simple and kind.
Hey ilî te'allemna we nihne kinna heyk tere ha bas ye'nî
inno te'allemna şuğlat ktîre fadetna kemane.
This is what we learned, and we used to be like that you
see, but I mean we learned many things that benefited us
too.
Misl eyş? xeyr înno besîtîn we tayyibîn.
Like what? Other than being simple and kind.
Misl kuli şî nindah moy mi c-cib...
Like everything, we draw water from the well...
Eywe...
Yes...
Nhûş zeytûn meselen înno nişteğil bi îdne.
We harvest olives for example, we work with our hands.
Te'temidû 'ela halikum.
You rely on yourselves.
E, ma kinna heyk.
Yes, we weren't like this.
Ye'nî...
I mean...
Kan yiştixil e-z-zeleme, e bas hallak sarna niswan we zilam.
The man used to work, yes, but now we women and men have
become workers.
El-heyat ferdet hala îcbarî.
Life imposed itself inevitably.
Ê mezbût.
Yes, exactly.
Ene mulahiz inno hal beyt 'ela besatito lakin hilû ktîr.
I noticed that this house, despite its simplicity, is very
beautiful.
Ê elhemdulellah.
Yes, praise be to God.
Înti zari'a hedol şuğlat?
Did you plant these things?
Ê.
Yes.
Ê elhemdulellah.
Yes, praise be to God.
'Addî li enwa'hum la şûf heyk...
Count their types for me let's see...
Hey lifleyfli zîne.. we hey ixta keman, haza hebeq xişin we
hebeq na'im...
These are ornamental peppers.. and this is its sister too,
this is coarse basil and fine basil...
Men qalû hon biqûlûlû rîhan?
Who said they call it rihan here?
Hon rîhan, intu bitqûlu hebeq.
Here it's rihan, you say habaq.
Hebeq.
Habaq.
Eywe, we haze l-'ineb. Şû zari'e keman?
Yes, and these grapes. What else have you planted?
Mentûr.
Wallflower.
Zeher.
Flowers.
Ma fî werid ke'inno ma fî zeher...
There are no roses as if there are no flowers...
Kaman zeher...
Also flowers...
هلا شو هذا سماق؟
Hello, what is this, sumac?
سماق، وفي دوالي، وفي جب تحت.
Sumac, and there are grape leaves, and a well down below.
هلا الضيعة فيها سماق؟
Now, does the village have sumac?
إيه سماق وزيتون وعوجة.
Yes, sumac, olives, and green almonds.
عوجة؟ لوزية؟
Green almonds? Almond trees?
لوز.
Almonds.
حلوة كتير، قدامك منظر كتير حلو.
Very beautiful, you have a very beautiful view in front of
you.
لا حلو الحمد لله.
No, it's beautiful, thank God.
كله زيتون وهون لما بطلي.
It's all olives, and here when you look out.
وكلياته إيه وراجو وكله مبين علينا هان.
And all of it, yes, Rajo and all of it is visible to us
here.
المناخ قلتلي كويس؟
You told me the climate is good?
كتير تمام.
Very perfect.
بالصيف وبالشتي شلون؟
In summer and winter, how is it?
وبالشتي تمام.
And in winter it's perfect.
بس بدو يكون عندك حطب منيح.
But you need to have good firewood.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
الصبية بنتك؟
Is the young lady your daughter?
تعالي شوفي نور.
Come see, Nour.
تعالي شوفي يا نور.
هلا شوفي.
Hello, look.
سلمي علينا طيب نور، يعني أنتي سلمي.
Greet us, well Nour, I mean you greet us.
يلا احكي.
Come on, speak.
نور الهدى.
Nour Al-Huda.
أهلاً وسهلاً يا نور الهدى، أهلاً وسهلاً فيكي.
Welcome Nour Al-Huda, welcome to you.
قديه عمرك؟
How old are you?
خجولة نور؟
Is Nour shy?
نور كتير، سبع سنين.
Nour is very shy, seven years old.
سبع سنين؟ اسم الله، إن شاء الله قطعتي كويس.
Seven years old? In the name of God, God willing you've
grown well.
إيه.
Yes.
الله يحميكي يا رب.
May God protect you, O Lord.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
الله يعطيكم العافية، شكراً إلكن، السلام عليكم.
May God give you health, thank you, peace be upon you.
شرفنا أهلي فيك، أهلاً وسهلاً.
You honored us, our people, welcome.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
هلا شباب، شلونك؟ جزاك الله خير. مرحبا، أهلاً وسهلاً يا هلا
الله يسلمك.
Hello guys, how are you? May God reward you. Hello, welcome,
hello, may God keep you safe.
حضرتك من هون ولا مهجر؟
Are you from here or displaced?
لا والله يا أخي نازح من عنجارة والله.
No, by God my brother, I am displaced from Anjara, by God.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
Oh, welcome to you.
حياك الله، أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
May God greet you, welcome to you.
هي مهنتك الأصلية؟
Is this your original profession?
إيه الحمد لله إيه.
Yes, thank God, yes.
الحمد لله، إيش اختلف عليك بالحلاقة بين عنجارة بريف حلب
الغربي وبين هون بعفرين بريف حلب الشمالي؟
Thank God, what differed for you in barbering between Anjara
in the western Aleppo countryside and here in Afrin in the
northern Aleppo countryside?
والله يا أخي كتير كتير، إيش اختلف؟
By God my brother, a whole lot, what differed?
يعني أولاً نفسية الواحد، تاني شيء يا أخي هنيك بلد كانت غير،
واحد بلده غير.
I mean, firstly, a person's psychological state, secondly my
brother, over there the town was different, one's own town
is different.
أكيد بلده غير، بس أنا عم بحكي على مستوى المهنة، القصات
اختلفت؟
For sure one's town is different, but I'm talking at the
level of the profession, did the haircuts differ?
إيه هلق طبعاً أكيد، والأجور اختلفت والموديلات اختلفت
والأجواء وحركة الشغل كله اختلف.
Yes, now of course for sure, and the wages differed, and the
styles differed, and the atmosphere, and the movement of
work, everything differed.
طب احكي لي هون على القصات.
Well, tell me about the haircuts here.
هلق هون أكتر شيء المارينز التركي والمارينز... يعني هيك
والحلاقات العادية.
Now here, the most common is the Turkish Marines and the
Marines... I mean like that, and regular haircuts.
أهل البلد شو بيحلقوا؟
What do the locals get for haircuts?
هلق بالنسبة لهون يعني إخوتنا الأكراد أكتر شيء مارينز تركي.
Now regarding here, I mean our Kurdish brothers, mostly
Turkish Marines.
تمام، والمهجرين؟
Okay, and the displaced?
المهجرين يعني ما في هالاهتمام الزيادة، أي موديل بيصير.
The displaced, I mean there isn't that extra interest, any
style works.
يعني الناس ما عندها هالنفس الزيادة الناس زي متل قبل.
I mean people don't have that extra desire like before.
تعبانة نفسيا؟
Psychologically tired?
كتير كتير.
Very, very.
طيب، الأخ منين؟
Okay, where is the brother from?
من حمص.
From Homs.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيكون.
Welcome to you.
الله يسلمك بابا عمرو.
May God keep you safe, Baba Amr.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً، أجدع رجال.
Oh, welcome, the bravest of men.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
احكيلي عن أهل بابا عمرو.
Tell me about the people of Baba Amr.
أهل بابا عمرو رجال وشباب وقبضايات وأهل نخوة.
The people of Baba Amr are men, youth, tough guys, and
people of chivalry.
أكيد أكيد ونعم منكم، أنتم يعني أسطورة بالثورة السورية صراحة.
For sure, for sure, and a blessing upon you, you are I mean
a legend in the Syrian revolution honestly.
أول ما بلشت الثورة السورية بابا عمرو كان إلها صيت.
When the Syrian revolution first started, Baba Amr had a
reputation.
بابا عمرو يعني الصخرة اللي تكسرت عليها عصابات الأسد.
Baba Amr is I mean the rock upon which Assad's gangs were
broken.
نحن ضلينا 28 يوم محاصرين، ما خليناهم يفوتوا، بعدين صار
اقتحام.
We remained besieged for 28 days, we didn't let them enter,
then an invasion happened.
أكيد بابا عمرو إلها طابع خاص وبصمة خاصة بالثورة السورية
والله، شقد انحصرتوا؟
For sure Baba Amr has a special character and a special mark
in the Syrian revolution by God, how long were you besieged?
قعدنا شي 28 يوم.
We stayed for about 28 days.
28 يوم بالظبط، فقط الحصار 28 يوم؟
28 days exactly, just the siege was 28 days?
28 يوم، وبعدها تم اقتحام الحي.
28 days, and after that the neighborhood was invaded.
تم الاقتحام.
It was invaded.
ذكرياتك الحلوة ببابا عمرو، إيش شو؟
Your sweet memories in Baba Amr, what are they?
ذكرياتي الحلوة كانت قبل الثورة، أما بالثورة كانت في حزن و...
My sweet memories were before the revolution, but during the
revolution there was sadness and...
سلامتك، تأثرت كتير، الله يوفقكم.
Your safety, you were deeply affected, may God grant you
success.
الله يرجعكم إن شاء الله.
May God return you, God willing.
الله يسلمك ويوفقك، هلق صار لنا شي عشر سنين طالعين من هنيك.
May God keep you safe and grant you success, now it's been
about ten years since we left there.
الله يرجعنا بجاه سيدنا محمد.
May God return us by the status of our master Muhammad.
آمين، ويرجع كل مهجر لبيته.
Amen, and may every displaced person return to their home.
بإذن الله، بإذن الله الله يسلمك.
God willing, God willing, may God keep you safe.
الله يعطيكم العافية، شكراً إلكن، السلام عليكم.
May God give you health, thank you, peace be upon you.
تاريخيا لا يوجد أي توثيق لتاريخ قرية حمشلك، ولا يعرف على وجه
التحديد التاريخ الحقيقي لنشوء هالقرية الحلوة الجميلة اللي
صايرة بحضن جبل من الطرف الشرقي.
Historically, there is no documentation for the history of
the village of Hamshelk, and the true date of the emergence
of this sweet, beautiful village located in the lap of a
mountain on the eastern side is not known precisely.
لكن أكثر الروايات تقول بأن عمر القرية يتجاوز الـ 300 سنة.
But most accounts say that the village's age exceeds 300
years.
لحتى نعرف أكثر عن تاريخ القرية وبداياتها وعوائلها ومنين أجت
الناس وكيفية يعني تجمعهم هون، رح يكون معنا مجموعة من الرجال
الكبار المسنين في القرية.
So that we can know more about the village's history, its
beginnings, its families, where the people came from, and
how I mean they gathered here, we will have with us a group
of the elderly men in the village.
ورح يكون معنا أيضا الدكتور محمد المصري اللي معه دكتوراه
بالتاريخ واللي ساكن بها القرية.
And we will also have with us Dr. Muhammad Al-Masri, who
holds a PhD in history and who lives in this village.
رح أبدأ بداية من عند عمي أبو علي، اللي هو واحد من يعني أكبر
الرجال هون واللي بيعرف تاريخ القرية.
I will start first with my uncle Abu Ali, who is one of, I
mean, the oldest men here and who knows the history of the
village.
عمي أبو علي، تحكي لنا حمشلك إيمتى بدايتها؟
My uncle Abu Ali, tell us, when did Hamshelk begin?
بدايتها من أكثر من 300 سنة، وتجمعت عدد العائلات اللي هون.
Its beginning was more than 300 years ago, and a number of
families gathered here.
أول عائلة كانت تبعت شو اسمه لحبيبه ساكنين فوق الجبل، نزحوا ع
زفنكه.
The first family was that of what's his name, Habiba, living
on top of the mountain, they moved to Zafnkeh.
بعد زفنكه توزعوا ع بعدنلي، في ناس نزلت ع بعدنلي في ناس نزلت
ع حمشلك.
After Zafnkeh they distributed to Baadanli, some people went
down to Baadanli, some people went down to Hamshelk.
المسميين، أول شيء كان قوبه، اسم اللحمة اللحمة قوبه، وحمشلك
اسم القش، مسميين حمشلك.
The names, the first thing was Qoubeh, the name of the clan
is Qoubeh, and Hamshelk is the name of the straw, they named
it Hamshelk.
وأربع عائلات، أول شيء عائلة تبع حمشلك ساكنين فيها، في ناس
سكنوا هون في ناس وزعوا لوين؟ عرب أوشاغي.
And four families, the first thing was the Hamshelk family
living in it, some people lived here, some people
distributed to where? Arab Ushaghi.
عرب أوشاغي بيت شيخو وبيت مسلم وبيت مراد هذول أساساً هون،
والتبعت لحبيبة تبعت زفنكه كانوا، ناس نزلت لهون ناس نزلت
بالبعدنلي.
Arab Ushaghi, the family of Sheikho, the family of Muslim,
and the family of Murad, these are originally here, and
those of Habiba, those of Zafnkeh, some people came down
here, some people went down in Baadanli.
يعني أهلاً وسهلاً، يعني أنا أفهم من كلامك، بأنه كان في
قريتين...
I mean welcome, I mean I understand from your words, that
there were two villages...
ثلاثة.
Three.
ثلاثة، بالأصل، لكن الثلاثة كانوا مشكلين حمشلك الغربية؟ اللي
نحن الآن فيها، التاريخية القديمة؟
Three, originally, but the three were forming Western
Hamshelk? Which we are in now, the old historical one?
الشرقية، الشرقية.
The Eastern, the Eastern.
الشرقية اللي بعدين توزعوا راحوا لعرب أوشاغي وبعدنلي وراحوا
لحمشلك التحتانية الغربية.
The Eastern, who then distributed, went to Arab Ushaghi and
Baadanli and went to the lower Western Hamshelk.
موهيك؟ بدي أروح للدكتور محمد، دكتور محمد تحكيلي شوي عن موقع
القرية تاريخياً يعني الحضارات الأقدم اللي موجودة هون الشواهد
التاريخية الأقدم وين هي؟
Isn't that right? I want to go to Dr. Muhammad, Dr.
Muhammad, tell me a bit about the village's location
historically, I mean the oldest civilizations that are
present here, the oldest historical evidence, where is it?
بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم، التاريخ بيتقدم عنا هون نحن من ما
يقارب 300 عام سابقا للتشكيل السكاني اللي صار بالقرية.
In the name of God, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
History advances for us here from approximately 300 years
ago prior to the demographic formation that happened in the
village.
أما الامتداد التاريخي اللي كان فينا هون فهو الامتداد بالحقبة
اليونانية ما بعد الحقبة الرومانية، ما بعد البيزنطية لحتى
امتدت للعثمانية.
As for the historical extension that was among us here, it
is the extension in the Greek era, after the Roman era,
after the Byzantine, until it extended to the Ottoman.
فالامتداد العثماني هن عبارة عن عائلة لجأت لهذا الجبل، فسكنوا
بالكهوف المغر، اللي هن بيسموها عندهم هون زقناق، اللي هي
المغر المهجورة طبعا.
So the Ottoman extension is a family that resorted to this
mountain, so they lived in the caves, the grottos, which
they call here "Zaqnaq," which are the abandoned grottos of
course.
ففيها كان آبار جاهزة، وفيها مغر جاهزة وفيها كهوف، فسكنوا
فيها هن وإبلهم وأغنامهم وكذا اللي هن...
So in them there were ready wells, and there were ready
grottos and caves, so they lived in them, they and their
camels and sheep and such, who are...
كهوف تعود للفترة اليونانية أم الرومانية؟
Caves dating back to the Greek or Roman period?
الحقبة الرومانية طبعا.
The Roman era of course.
فلجأوا إليها وسكنوا فيها وقعدوا اللي هن ما يعني نحن بنسميهم
بيت حبيب أو حمشلك، عائلة حمشلك.
So they resorted to them and lived in them and stayed, who
are what I mean we call the Habib family or Hamshelk, the
Hamshelk family.
حبيب وحمشلك واحد؟
Are Habib and Hamshelk one?
لا، أكيد لا، هن كل، كل مين عائلة لوحد يعني.
No, definitely not, they are each, each one is a separate
family I mean.
فقعدوا في جنبهم مباشرة قرية اللي هي نفسها اللي نحن قاعدين
فيها هي علي بالو، علي بالو الغربية طبعاً حمشلك الفوقا.
So right next to them they stayed in a village, which is the
same one we are sitting in, it's Ali Balo, Western Ali Balo
of course, Upper Hamshelk.
بعدين نزحوا لتحت، لجأوا لتحت يعني اللي صارت حمشلك التحت،
اللي هي قوبه، سميت قوبه.
Then they moved downwards, they resorted downwards, I mean
what became Lower Hamshelk, which is Qoubeh, named Qoubeh.
فهي الامتداد التاريخي للقرية كلياتها، وهي عبارة عن أربع أو
خمس عائلات.
So this is the historical extension of the entire village,
and it consists of four or five families.
وفي مقولة ثانية بتقول هي قبيلة البين، القبيلة الأقدم
الكردية.
And there is another saying that says it is the Al-Bayn
tribe, the oldest Kurdish tribe.
فهاي جبال عنا هون هذا الجبل هون امتداد جبل هذا جبال حبيب،
سلسلة جبال حبيب، أو ما نسميها نحن مثلا جبال كولو، جبال
الكولو هون.
So these mountains we have here, this mountain here is an
extension of a mountain, these are the Habib Mountains, the
Habib Mountain range, or what we call for example the Kolo
Mountains, the Kolo Mountains here.
فهي جبال بالأساس كانت بالحكم الروماني كان إلها حكم وكان إلها
نفوذ وكان إلها سلطة ومأهولة سكانياً من قبل التاريخ، قديمة
جدا يعني ما يقارب أستاذ مصطفى...
So they are mountains that originally, under Roman rule, had
governance, had influence, had authority, and were inhabited
by a population since prehistory, very ancient, I mean
approximately Mr. Mustafa...
يعطيك العافية دكتور محمد. عمي أبو محمد يعني الآن أنا فهمت
أنه في حمشلك وفي حبيب.
May God give you health, Dr. Muhammad. My uncle Abu
Muhammad, I mean now I understand that there is Hamshelk and
there is Habib.
حمشلك والعوائل الكردية بينتموا لعشيرة بين الكردية، وحبيب من
عمي من العرب مزبوط؟
Hamshelk and the Kurdish families belong to the Kurdish Al-
Bayn clan, and Habib, my uncle, is from the Arabs, correct?
يعني هذول عائلة حبيب لحالهم عائلة كبيرة.
I mean these are the Habib family, on their own they are a
large family.
صحيح.
True.
والحمشلك بحالهم.
And the Hamshelk on their own.
صحيح.
True.
وعلي بالو بحالهم هذول ثلاث عائلات.
And Ali Balo on their own, these are three families.
نعم ثلاث تجمعات.
Yes, three gatherings.
وشفت هالعلي بالو شفت بيوتهم لسا على أساس؟ هذول بيوتهم.
And did you see this Ali Balo, did you see their houses
still on their foundations? These are their houses.
علي بالو حبيب وحمشلك.
Ali Balo, Habib, and Hamshelk.
صحيح.
True.
هذول الأساسي بهالضيعة هي، الحمشلك نحن الأساس.
These are the core in this village, we the Hamshelk are the
core.
كونوا مع بعضهم هم وبيت عمكم، هالضيعة هاي زمانا قتلوا مع
بعضهم قتلوا زلمة في بعضهم.
They were together, them and your uncle's family, this
village long ago they fought with each other, they killed a
man among themselves.
للأسف.
Unfortunately.
باليتيمة.
In Al-Yatima.
إيوه.
Yes.
إيه، هذا مع تركيا، جماعتنا هذا مع تركيا، اللي جعل مثل هالجد
يعني، راعي اجى قعد هون.
Yes, this one is with Turkey, our group this one is with
Turkey, who made it like this grandfather I mean, a shepherd
came and settled here.
بعد منه بكم سنة اجوا من هنيك اجوا العرب شاغي، سكنوا هون يعني
على أساس ضيعة إلنا حمشلك من هنيك.
A few years after him, they came from over there, the Arab
Shaghi came, they settled here I mean on the basis that it
is our village, Hamshelk, from over there.
هن صاروا شيء 400، 500 بيت صاروا حمشلك، من عائلتنا نحن ما
بنعرف عنهم شيء.
They became some 400, 500 houses that became Hamshelk, from
our family, we don't know anything about them.
تمام.
Okay.
يعني نحن هون الحمشلك الأساس.
I mean we here, the Hamshelk, are the core.
إيش كنتوا تشتغلوا؟
What did you use to work in?
حاوي ماعز وغنم وبقر.
Raising goats, sheep, and cows.
بقر.
Cows.
و، يعني في هون كان مي؟ سكنوا هون كان في مي ولا منين كانوا؟
And, I mean, was there water here? They settled here, was
there water, or where did they get it from?
في صهاريج، في صهاريج، شوف هذا تحت الترومبة شفته؟
There are cisterns, there are cisterns, see this under the
pump, did you see it?
هذا قديم من 300 سنة تحت الترومبة، شفت هالصاريج عتيقة بير.
This is old, from 300 years ago under the pump, did you see
these ancient cisterns, a well.
يعني بجي مصافي أكثر منه.
I mean, it acts as a filter more than anything.
تمام، خلينا نروح للمختار، عمي عدنان، حضرتك أبو عارف،
مختار...
Okay, let's go to the Mukhtar, my uncle Adnan, you are Abu
Aref, the Mukhtar of...
ضيعة، انتم من بيت حبيب، وبيت حبيب هن عائلة عربية من عشيرة
النعيم استكردوا.
A village... you are from the Habib family, and the Habib
family is an Arab family from the Al-Naim tribe who became
Kurdified.
مزبوط؟ انتم من كم سنة هون؟ احكي لي عن علاقتكم مع بعض، انتم
وكل أهل الضيعة.
Right? How many years have you been here? Tell me about your
relationship with each other, you and all the people of the
village.
كيف عشتوا؟ وكيف تعلمتوا منهم يعني اللغة؟ وكيف عاداتكم صارت؟
شو... احكي لي عن هالموضوع هذا.
How did you live? And how did you learn the language from
them? And how did your customs become? What... tell me about
this topic.
من زمان سكنوا هون أجدادنا، سكنوا هون. وعاشرناهم، نحن كلياتنا
إخوة.
Our ancestors lived here a long time ago, they lived here.
And we mixed with them, we are all brothers.
تعايشنا سوا، وعطينا نسوان لبعض، وأخذنا من بعض. هذا هو.
We coexisted together, and we gave women to each other, and
we took from each other. That's it.
في فرق بين الاستعراب وبين الاستكراد، مثلاً نحن عنا مثلاً
عائلة حبيب،
There is a difference between Arabization and Kurdification,
for example, we have the Habib family,
أثناء ما انوجدوا هن، من الأساس عشيرة النعيم، عز الدين حمرا،
اللي إجوا لهون هن.
when they first appeared, they are originally from the Al-
Naim tribe, Izz al-Din Hamra, who came here.
تقريباً عمرهم ما يقارب 230 سنة، 240، 230 سنة، هم قديمين.
They are approximately 230 years old, 240, 230 years, they
are old.
فهن اللي قبلهم كانوا على بالو موجودين، اللي هن الأساسيين
حمشلك.
So the ones before them were the Ali Balo family, who are
the original ones of Hamshalk.
التاريخ هيك بيحكي طبعاً نحن مو انه يعني.
That is what history says, of course, it's not that we
just...
فكان المكان موجود، جاهز مأهول لإلهم.
So the place was there, ready and inhabited for them.
يعني سابقاً.
Prepared.
I mean, previously.
أيوه مهيأ طبعاً، مهيأ مناخياً وطبيعياً وكذا، فقعدوا وسكنوا
بزقناق.
Yes, prepared of course, prepared climatically, naturally,
and so on, so they stayed and lived in Zaqnaq.
ومنا هي علي بالو، ومنا يعني استدرجوا في التاريخ، وحطوا بناء،
وحطوا عمار، وحطوا كذا، وصاروا هون هن استكردوا.
And from there to Ali Balo, and from there they gradually
progressed in history, and they put up buildings, and they
built, and so on, and they became Kurdified here.
يعني الأساس اللي موجودين عائلة حمشلك، هن أكراد.
I mean, the original ones who are present, the Hamshalk
family, are Kurds.
فعائلة حبيب استكردوا معهم.
So the Habib family became Kurdified with them.
فإجت بعدهم عائلة مسلم أو عائلة بيت شيخو ومسلم، اللي إجوا هن
بعدين هون.
Then after them came the Muslim family, or the family of
Beit Sheikho and Muslim, who came here later.
هن أربع خمس عائلات موجودين بالضيعة يعني تقريباً ما يقارب.
There are four or five families in the village,
approximately.
وقرية صغيرة يعني تعتبر قرية نائية صغيرة يعني هي حمشلك التحتة
أو الفوقة.
And it's a small village, I mean it's considered a small
remote village, whether it's lower Hamshalk or upper.
الأهالي هون كلهم، من كل المكونين، بيحكوا اللغة الكردية، ولا
سمحت...
The people here, from both components, all speak the Kurdish
language, excuse me...
تفضل.
Go ahead.
الأهالي هون كلهم بيحكوا اللغة الكردية فقط أم بيحكوا اللغة
الكردية والعربية؟
Do the people here all speak only the Kurdish language, or
do they speak Kurdish and Arabic?
أكيد طبعاً الأهالي هون أكيد يعني هن.
Sure, of course, the people here, absolutely.
القدامى فيهم، الكبار بالعمر أو بالسن، غالباً تجدهم يعني ما
بيتقنوا اللغة العربية نهائياً.
The older ones among them, the elderly, you will often find
that they do not master the Arabic language at all.
فالأجيال المعاصرة أتقنت اللغة العربية نسبة لتعلمهم بمدارسنا
وجامعاتنا وكذا،
So the contemporary generations mastered the Arabic language
due to their learning in our schools, universities, and so
on,
ونسبة للدراسة وهالأمور هي، فأتقنوا اللغة العربية.
and due to studying and these things, so they mastered the
Arabic language.
فتجد هون في القرية، المعمرين أو في الكبار في العمر، أغلبهم
لا يتقنون اللغة العربية، أو يتقنونها بشكل بسيط جداً.
So you find here in the village, the elderly or the older
people, most of them do not master the Arabic language, or
they master it very simply.
أو مثلاً تحكي أنت عربي معه فيفهم عليك فما بيعرف يرد عليك
باللغة العربية.
Or for example, you speak Arabic with him, he understands
you, but he doesn't know how to reply to you in Arabic.
الله يعطيكم العافية، شكراً لكم.
May God give you health, thank you.
أهلا وسهلا.
You are welcome.
على الرغم من صغر حجم حمشلك وبساطتها وطابعها الزراعي الريفي،
لكن لا يخلو الأمر من وجود حرف ومهن.
Despite the small size of Hamshalk, its simplicity, and its
rural agricultural character, it is not without the presence
of crafts and professions.
وأولادها كانوا يشتغلوا بالأصل ببعض الحرف والمهن، ومنهم يعني
حرفة الخياطة وربما أيضاً الأحذية،
And its people originally worked in some crafts and
professions, including the tailoring profession and perhaps
also shoes,
وأيضاً هناك الحدادة والميكانيك.
and there is also blacksmithing and mechanics.
حالياً بهالقرية الصغيرة في ورشة وحدة لصناعة الأفران، أفران
الكعك.
Currently, in this small village, there is one workshop for
manufacturing ovens, cake ovens.
هالورشة موجودة من عام 2014 وما زالت عم تشتغل وبتصنع أفران
لكافة المناطق المحررة.
This workshop has been here since 2014 and is still working
and manufacturing ovens for all the liberated areas.
رح نزورها معكم ونتعرف عن واقع هالورشة وواقع الحرف والمهن
بالمنطقة بالعموم، وكيف مستمرين وشو هي آفاق العمل. تفضلوا
معنا.
We will visit it with you and learn about the reality of
this workshop and the reality of crafts and professions in
the region in general, how they are continuing, and what the
work prospects are. Come with us.
يا رب. السلام عليكم.
Oh God. Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
أهلا وسهلا، يا مية السلامة، الحمد لله.
Welcome, a hundred welcomes, praise be to God.
شلونك؟ نتعرف عليك.
How are you? Let's get to know you.
أنا اسمي نوري مصطفى.
My name is Nouri Mustafa.
أهلا وسهلا فيك.
You are very welcome.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
نعم، الحمد لله.
You welcome us to the workshop.
Yes, praise be to God.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
احكي لي عن هالورشة شوي، شقد عمرها؟ ايش وضعها؟
Tell me a bit about this workshop, how old is it? What is
its situation?
والله ورشة تصنيع أفران خبز وكعك، هون نحن بنشتغل.
Well, it's a workshop for manufacturing bread and cake
ovens, we work here.
بـ 2003 فتحت، كنت بحلب.
It opened in 2003, I was in Aleppo.
طلعت لهون بـ 2014، واستقريت هون الحمد لله عم بشتغل هلق.
I came here in 2014, and I settled here, praise be to God, I
am working now.
نفس الورشة اللي كانت بحلب صارت هون؟
The same workshop that was in Aleppo is now here?
نفس الورشة، كنت بالشيخ نجار وانتقلت لهون.
The same workshop, I was in Sheikh Najjar and I moved here.
كان عندك معمل ولا ورشة؟
Did you have a factory or a workshop?
والله عندي معمل كان. نحن بنصنع أفران خبز وكعك. حالياً.
Well, I had a factory. We manufacture bread and cake ovens.
Currently.
تمام، وهلق عندك فرن كعك عم تشتغل فيه؟
Alright, and now you have a cake oven that you are working
on?
إي هلق عندي فرن كعك عم بشتغل فيه.
Yes, now I have a cake oven that I'm working on.
أيوه، فرن كعك. ومن 2014 أنت هون؟
I see, a cake oven. And you've been here since 2014?
من 2014 أنا هون.
I have been here since 2014.
احكي لي، قبل ما ندخل في تفاصيل الورشة، يعني شلون هون مناخ
الشغل؟ مناخ العمل؟ بالنسبة إلكون؟
Tell me, before we get into the details of the workshop, how
is the work climate here? The work environment? For you?
مناخ الشغل نحن يعني متطرفين الحمد لله ومبسوطين يعني، لا عنا
زحمة، لا عنا عجقة.
The work climate, we are on the outskirts, praise be to God,
and we are happy, we don't have traffic, we don't have
crowding.
وبجي... يعني شغلنا كله طيار يعني. يعني بنشتغل.
And I come... I mean, our work is all smooth. I mean, we
work.
أقصد أقصد الظرف بالقرية مناسب ومساعد للشغل؟
I mean, are the conditions in the village suitable and
helpful for the work?
يعني مساعد، عمالي كلهم من هون بالورشة عم يشتغلوا.
Yes, helpful, all my workers are from here, working in the
workshop.
عمالك من وين؟
Where are your workers from?
من الورشة من هون، نفس...
From the workshop here, the same...
نعم.
From the village, you mean?
Yes.
كم عامل عندك؟
How many workers do you have?
عندي 7.
I have 7.
نعم.
7 workers.
Yes.
بيشتغلوا بشكل دائم؟ مصدر رزقهم من هون؟
Do they work permanently? Is their source of income from
here?
بشكل دائم، الحمد لله نعم.
Permanently, praise be to God, yes.
خلينا نمشي شوي، هلق هذا هذا فرن كعك قلت لي؟
Let's walk a bit, now this, this is a cake oven you told me?
عندي هذا فرن كعك، هذا تبع مجرى البخار، هون عم بشتغل فيه.
I have this cake oven, this is the one for the steam duct,
I'm working on it here.
إي، هذا بيخلص إن شاء الله بحطه جواته. نعم.
Yes, when this is finished, God willing, I will put it
inside it. Yes.
وهذا شو هذا؟
And what is this?
هذا فرن كعك.
This is a cake oven.
نعم.
Also cake?
Yes.
هدول يعني هدول لهدول ولا كل شيء لحال؟
These, I mean, are these for these, or is everything
separate?
هاد لجوا بيركب، هاد لهون، هون بيعطي بخار للصمون. بنشتغل.
This one is installed inside, this one is for here, here it
gives steam to the samoon bread. We work.
طيب المواد الأولية من أيمت بتجيبوها؟
Alright, where do you get the raw materials from?
والله المواد الأولية أكتر شيء منجيبها من الباب.
Well, most of the raw materials we get from Al-Bab.
من الباب؟
From Al-Bab?
نعم.
Yes.
متوفر هنيك أحسن، أكتر.
Why?
It's available there better, more.
تمام. كل المواد الأولية؟ حتى مثلاً، مواد الإلكترونية، مواد
كهربائية؟
Alright. All the raw materials? Even, for example,
electronic materials, electrical materials?
مواد الإلكترونية منجيبها من تركيا.
The electronic materials we get from Turkey.
متوفرة؟
Are they available?
متوفرة كله.
They are all available.
وأسعارها شلون؟
And how are their prices?
أسعارها والله أحسن يعني، أسعارها كتير مناسبة.
Their prices are actually better, their prices are very
reasonable.
نعم.
Reasonable?
Yes.
ووين بتشتغلوا؟ فرص عملكم لوين بتشتغلوا؟ يعني وين بتاخدوا
بضاعتكم؟ وين بتاخدوا أفرانكم؟
And where do you work? Where do your job opportunities go? I
mean, where do you take your goods? Where do you take your
ovens?
بضاعتنا نحن بس خلصت بالريف الغربي، إعزاز، جرابلس، الباب، هون
عفرين.
Our goods, once finished, go to the western countryside,
Azaz, Jarabulus, Al-Bab, here in Afrin.
بتشتغلوا أنتم توصيات ولا بتشتغلوا لقدام وبتبيعوا بعدين؟
Do you work by custom orders, or do you work ahead and sell
later?
نحن، نحن توصيات. توصيات كله يعني، تواصي.
We, we do custom orders. Custom orders mostly, by order.
نعم.
By order.
Yes.
إيش في أقسام المعمل هون؟ الورشة؟
What sections are in the factory here? The workshop?
أقسام المعمل متل شو؟
The factory sections like what?
يعني أقسام الورشة، إيش المعدات، إيش الآليات؟
I mean the sections of the workshop, what are the equipment,
what are the machines?
المعدات عندي فريزة هون، مثقب فريزة، عندي مثقب ثابت.
The equipment, I have a milling machine here, a milling
drill, I have a stationary drill.
عندي تورنو هون عندي. عندي طعاجة. عندي مقص يدوي.
I have a lathe here. I have a bending machine. I have manual
shears.
وهون يعني بنشئ فيها الورشة، بنشتغل.
And here we build them in the workshop, we work.
بنشئ فيها الورشة. هلق أنت قلت لي أفران كعك.
Build them in the workshop. Now you told me cake ovens.
نعم.
Yes.
أفران الكعك، كل نوع من الكعك يحتاج إلى فرن خاص، ولا الفرن
نفسه بيصنع أنواع مختلفة من الكعك؟
Cake ovens, does each type of cake need a specific oven, or
does the same oven make different types of cake?
بالنسبة لفرن الكعك، بتشتغل فيه جميع أصناف الحلويات
والمعجنات.
Regarding the cake oven, you can bake all kinds of sweets
and pastries in it.
من عش البلبل للحلويات.
From Osh El Bulbul to all sweets.
كل الأنواع؟
All types?
كل الأنواع. ما في شيء يعني، هاد للصمون، هاد للكعك، هاد
للكرواسان، لأ.
All types. There is no such thing as this is for samoon,
this is for cake, this is for croissant, no.
هون بيلعب دور مين؟ دور العجان، دور المصنع اللي بيشتغل
بالعجين.
Here, who plays the role? The role of the dough mixer, the
role of the maker who works with the dough.
هلق نحن مثلاً بنعرف إنه مثلاً المعروك أو الكعك في تركيا، غير
بسوريا، غير بالسعودية، غير بلبنان.
Now, for example, we know that Maarouk or cake in Turkey is
different than in Syria, different than in Saudi Arabia,
different than in Lebanon.
نحن عنا، بسوريا بنشتغل كل شيء، صمون، حلويات، معجنات.
For us, in Syria we make everything, samoon, sweets,
pastries.
أما بتركيا بيشتغلوا عبارة عن صمون بيختلف عنا، أفرانهم نفس
أفراننا.
But in Turkey they mainly make samoon which differs from
ours, their ovens are the same as our ovens.
نفس الأفران؟
The same ovens?
نفس الأفران.
The same ovens.
هي الأفران بتشتغل على الكهربا ولا على؟
Do these ovens work on electricity or on...?
بتشتغل على الديزل.
They work on diesel.
نعم.
On diesel?
Yes.
وعلى الكهربا؟
And on electricity?
وعلى الكهربا، بتساعده.
And on electricity, it assists it.
شقد تكلفة الفرن حالياً؟
How much does the oven cost currently?
تكلفة الفرن حالياً، يعني عم نحكي بالدولار تقريباً. شي 8500
دولار.
The cost of the oven currently, I mean we are talking in
dollars roughly. About $8,500.
فرن الكعك نعم. بيجي معه أربع عربيات، عربية صمون وثلاث عربيات
تبعت يعني معروك وحلويات وكعك وهيك شيء.
This cake oven?
فرن الكعك نعم. بيجي معه أربع عربيات، عربية صمون وثلاث عربيات
تبعت يعني معروك وحلويات وكعك وهيك شيء.
The cake oven, yes. It comes with four trolleys, one trolley
for samoon and three trolleys for Maarouk, sweets, cakes,
and things like that.
جربت تساووا فرن خبز؟
Have you tried making a bread oven?
لكا، عندي، صنعت. ركبت براجو وفي شغال هلق حالياً.
Of course, I have, I manufactured one. I installed it in
Rajo and it is currently working.
في شغل يعني؟
There is work then?
هلق الطلبات عم تجيكم من هون ولا من منطقة إدلب؟
Yes.
Now, do the orders come to you from here or from the Idlib
region?
والله أكتر شيء منطقة إدلب.
Actually, mostly from the Idlib region.
منطقة إدلب؟
The Idlib region?
أنا شغال أكتر من عفرين.
I work there more than in Afrin.
فيها حيوية أكتر؟
Is it more dynamic there?
نعم نعم. فيها حيوية.
Yes, yes. It is dynamic.
هاد المكان شو كان قبل؟
What was this place before?
كانت معصرة والله.
It was an olive press, indeed.
معصرة زيتون. نعم. إجيت لهون نزحت، واستأجرته، وضليت فيه مبرك
يعني.
Yes.
معصرة زيتون. نعم. إجيت لهون نزحت، واستأجرته، وضليت فيه مبرك
يعني.
An olive press. Yes. I came here displaced, rented it, and
stayed settled in it.
من 2014.
Since 2014.
شو الصعوبات اللي عم تواجهكم حالياً؟
What are the difficulties you are facing currently?
والله صعوبات ما في شيء، نحن الحمد لله، عندي سيارة، بجيب
عمالي، في منهم هون بيشتغلوا عندي عمالي، وبروح وبجي، دوامي
الساعة 8 للـ 5 بننصرف.
Well, there are no difficulties at all, praise be to God, we
have a car, I bring my workers, some of my workers work
here, and I commute, my working hours are from 8 to 5 and we
leave.
أنا ما هذا قصدي، قصدي مثلاً صعوبات تتعلق بـ مثلاً إنه في
جمود بالسوق؟
That is not what I meant, I mean, for example, difficulties
related to, let's say, stagnation in the market?
مثلاً غلاء في المواد الأولية؟
For example, high prices of raw materials?
هلق غلاء في مواد أولية، يعني ما دام بالدولار ما بأثر
عالمصنع.
Now regarding the high prices of raw materials, as long as
it's in dollars, it doesn't affect the manufacturer.
لا، بس المستهلك ما بقى يشتري؟
No, but the consumer stops buying?
المستهلك بيشتري. كمان بيبيع بالدولار هو.
The consumer buys. Because they also sell in dollars.
لكا.
I see.
Of course.
تمام. يعني ما عندك مشكلة، ما دام في المواد الأولية. لكن أنا
ملاحظ إنه واقفين الآن، ليش؟
Alright. I mean you have no problem, as long as there are
raw materials. But I noticed that they are standing still
now, why?
متل شو؟ واقفين ما عم يشتغلوا؟ يعني هلق أنا عم بصفح فرن
حالياً، عم تشتغل فيه، نعم.
Like what? Standing still not working? I mean now I am
sheeting an oven currently, you are working on it, yes.
وراه عندي واحد تاني إن شاء الله.
And behind it?
Behind it I have another one, God willing.
يا رب الله يفتح عليكم.
Oh God, may God open doors for you.
في سؤال يعني عم يخطر على بالي اسألك ياه، وجود الورشة هون في
الضيعة هي البسيطة اللي اسمها حمشلك، شو أضاف للضيعة؟
There is a question that comes to my mind to ask you, the
presence of the workshop here in this simple village called
Hamshalk, what did it add to the village?
والله أضاف نشاط للضيعة، يعني عامل بدل ما يروح يشتغل بعفرين،
ويحط أجار مواصلات، شغله جنب بيته.
Well, it added activity to the village. A worker, instead of
going to work in Afrin and paying for transportation, his
work is next to his house.
يعني العامل بيرتاح وأنا برتاح يعني.
I mean, the worker is comfortable and I am comfortable.
يعني عجقة السوق ووضع البلد بتعرف، هالتفجيرات وهالمشاكل اللي
عم بتصير بعفرين، هون عنا آمن يعني الحمد لله.
I mean, the crowded market and the situation of the country,
you know, these bombings and problems happening in Afrin,
here it is safe for us, praise be to God.
يعني مناخ مناسب لإنه يكون في نشاط مهني حرفي صناعي؟
Meaning a suitable climate for having professional,
artisanal, and industrial activity?
طبعاً. يعني بتعد حالك أنت هون يعني عم تشتغل كأنه جاية سيران
يعني.
Of course. I mean, you consider yourself here, working as if
you are on a picnic.
تمام.
Alright.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
بارك الله فيك، أهلاً وسهلاً، سلامات.
God bless you, welcome, goodbye.
الله يعطيك العافية يا أبو زورو.
God give you health, Abu Zoro.
الله يعافيك أهلا وسهلا بك.
God give you health, welcome.
نوري وأبو زورو عازفين بزق من قرية عمر أوشاغي...
Nouri and Abu Zoro are two Buzuq players from the village of
Omar Oshaghi...
المجاورة لحمشلك. اليوم شفناهم بالصدفة...
...adjacent to Hamshalak. Today we saw them by chance...
جايين لعند أبو محمد، صاحب البيت، جايين بضيافته.
...coming to Abu Muhammad, the owner of the house, coming as
his guests.
ونحنا يعني سرقناهم سرقة، سرقنا منهم الوقت سرقة...
And we, you know, stole them a bit, we stole some time from
them...
لنتعرف شوي على الفلكلور الغنائي لقرية حمشلك...
...to learn a little about the vocal folklore of the village
of Hamshalak...
وعمر أوشاغي وبعدنلي وهالمنطقة هاي.
...Omar Oshaghi, Badinli, and this region.
هلق شو كنت عم تعزف أبو زورو؟
Now, what were you playing, Abu Zoro?
والله كان هيك لحن كردي ومميز يعني.
Well, it was like this, a Kurdish melody and distinct, you
know.
شو اسمه هاد اللحن؟
What is the name of this melody?
هاللحن هي تقسيم...
This melody is a taqsim...
يعني أول بداية مثلا إذا بدك تغني...
...meaning, at the beginning, for example, if you want to
sing...
مثلا أي أغنية كردية، مقام ثقيل يعني...
...for example, any Kurdish song, a heavy maqam, you know...
بتسبقها بهالتقسيم.
...is preceded by this taqsim.
تقاسيم، يعني بداية.
Taqasim, I mean, a prelude.
إيوا، نعم.
Yes, indeed.
بدي أسأل نوري...
I want to ask Nouri...
بتجي عـ الأغنيات، مثلا أي أغنية بده...
It introduces the songs, for example, whichever song he
wants...
مثلا بيفوتوا عليها.
...for example, it goes into it.
تمام. نوري بدي أسألك سؤال.
Alright. Nouri, I want to ask you a question.
أنا لاحظت من خلال تجوالنا في هالمناطق...
I noticed during our tour in these areas...
إنه الأكراد هنن من أكثر الشعوب محافظة واهتماماً بتراثهم
الغنائي والفلكلوري.
...that Kurds are among the people who most preserve and
care about their vocal and folklore heritage.
شو السبب؟ في ارتباط كبير بينهم وبين هالفلكلور.
What's the reason? There is a great connection between them
and this folklore.
لأن الجبال كمان قريبة من الموسيقى.
Because the mountains are also close to music.
إذا تروح عـ الجبال كمان في موسيقى.
If you go to the mountains, there is also music.
من صوت عصافير.
From the sound of birds.
يعني في لحن بقلب الجبل.
I mean, there is a melody in the mountain.
يا سلام. أولاد الطبيعة.
Beautiful. Children of nature.
من هالشي الأكراد مرتبطين باللحن، موسيقى.
Because of this, Kurds are connected to melody and music.
أولاد الطبيعة. صوت الرياح بالجبل، صوت العصافير، الحيوانات...
Children of nature. Sound of the wind in the mountain, sound
of birds, animals...
أوراق الشجر.
Exactly.
...tree leaves.
بالضبط.
Exactly.
يا سلام. هلق شو عم يعزف أبو زورو؟
Beautiful. Now what is Abu Zoro playing?
أبو زورو عم يعزف أغنية مريمة.
Abu Zoro is playing the song Meryemê.
مريمة هلق.
Meryemê now.
بدي قبل ما أنتقل، أرجع لعندكم عـ الموسيقى، بدي أسأل أبو
محمد.
Before moving on, let me get back to your music, let me ask
Abu Muhammad.
أبو محمد، بدي أسألك سؤال...
Abu Muhammad, I want to ask you a question...
هنن الآن شباب بضيافتك، وواضح إنه أنت مستمتع بالعزف تبعهم.
They are currently guests at your house, and it's clear you
are enjoying their playing.
إيشو اللي لفت نظرك أكتر شي بالفلكلور الغنائي لهالمنطقة؟
What caught your attention the most in the vocal folklore of
this region?
والله بالنسبة للعزف اللي عم يعزفوه الشباب أنا شفته قريب كتير
من الموسيقى العربية.
Well, regarding the playing that the young men are doing, I
found it very close to Arabic music.
وخصوصا لما نحن عندنا بالجبل هنيك، عزف العود.
Especially when we are in the mountain there, playing the
oud.
يعني كتير، كتير قريب، أول شكل، كشكل للبزق اللي عم يشتغلوا
عليه شكله قريب من العود.
Very close, first the shape... the shape of the buzuq they
are working on, its shape is close to the oud.
وبنفس الوقت حتى الألحان...
At the same time, even the melodies...
أغلبيتها عم تيجي عم بفهمها أنا.
...most of the melodies are coming... I understand them.
عم بغني معها عربي، بحس حالي عم بغني معها عربي أنا.
I'm singing Arabic with it, I feel like I'm singing Arabic
with it.
في تماهي بين الألحان العربية والكردية.
There is an overlap between the Arabic and Kurdish melodies.
أكيد. أكيد.
Definitely. Definitely.
تمام. شو رح تسمعونا هلق؟
Alright. What are you going to play for us now?
اللي بدك ياه يعني.
Whatever you want.
أنا بدي اللي بدك ياه أنت.
I want what you want.
شو هاد اللحن اللي عزفته؟
What is this melody you just played?
هادا أغنية تركية أصلا.
This is a Turkish song originally.
وإلها يعني... في كردي عم يغني عليها، في عربي عم يغني عليها.
And it has... I mean, a Kurd sings it, an Arab sings it.
المطرب الأساسي اسمه مصطفى أوغور، من تركيا.
The main singer is named Mustafa Uğur, from Turkey.
نعم.
Yes.
فيك تغني؟
Can you sing?
بالتركي؟ بالكردي؟ بالعربي؟
In Turkish? Kurdish? In Arabic?
بالكردي.
In Kurdish.
الكردي ماني حافظ أغاني كتير أنا.
I don't know many Kurdish ones by heart.
إيشو شو؟ شو بدك تغني؟ شو بدك تغني؟
What? What do you want to sing? What do you want to sing?
عربي، كردي، اللي بدك. شو بدك تغني؟
Arabic, Kurdish, whatever you want. What do you want to
sing?
سمعتك أنت عم تقول قبل شوي بدك تسمعني شي تاني ما بعرف.
I heard you earlier saying you'd sing me something else, I
don't know.
Oy felekê, ka bêje vê emrê min ku da çû?
Oh fate, tell me, where did my life go?
Havîn û zivistan, bihar û payîz zaya çû.
Summer and winter, spring and autumn went to waste.
Dildar bibûm, hêsîr û koletiya evînê da çû.
I was a lover, my life went into the captivity and slavery
of love.
Firxa hinarê, gewr pêsîrê, xatir nexwest çû.
The pomegranate sprout, with a fair breast, left without
saying goodbye.
Firxa hinarê, gewr pêsîrê, xatir nexwest çû.
The pomegranate sprout, with a fair breast, left without
saying goodbye.
Dildar bibûm, hêsîr û koletiya evînê da çû.
I was a lover, my life went into the captivity and slavery
of love.
Firxa hinarê, gewr pêsîrê, xatir nexwest çû.
The pomegranate sprout, with a fair breast, left without
saying goodbye.
Firxa hinarê, gewr pêsîrê, xatir nexwest çû.
The pomegranate sprout, with a fair breast, left without
saying goodbye.
Por sipî bû, diran weşiyan, evîniya'm fêda çû.
My hair turned white, my teeth fell out, my love went in
vain.
Dil û cegerê min heliyan, êş û jan kete çû.
My heart and liver melted, pain and suffering took over.
Gund û welatan digerim, taqet nema çû.
I wander through villages and countries, my strength is
gone.
Dost û hevalên dor û dera, te ez hîştim çû.
The friends and companions around, you left me and went.
Gund û welatan digerim, taqet nema çû.
I wander through villages and countries, my strength is
gone.
Dost û hevalên dor û dera, te ez hîştim çû.
The friends and companions around, you left me and went.
الله يعطيكم العافية يا رب، شكرا كتير.
God give you health, thank you so much.
فعلا عزفك وعزف أبو زورو كتير حلو.
Truly, your playing and Abu Zoro's playing is very
beautiful.
ذكرتونا بأصوات الطبيعة...
You reminded us of the sounds of nature...
أصوات الريح في الجبال وأصوات العصافير...
...the sounds of the wind in the mountains and the sounds of
birds...
والطبيعة الحلوة كمان بالحقول.
...and the beautiful nature in the fields as well.
يعطيكن العافية مع السلامة يا رب.
God give you health, peace be upon you.
الله يسلمكم. أعزائي المشاهدين رح نختم معكم هالحلقة...
God keep you safe. Dear viewers, we conclude this episode
with you...
لنكون معكم إن شاء الله في الأسبوع القادم...
...to be with you, God willing, next week...
بحلقة جديدة وقرية جديدة.
...in a new episode and a new village.
بدنا منكم تعليقاتكم على هالحلقة...
We want your comments on this episode...
واقتراحاتكم لمناطق سورية حلوة كمان...
...and your suggestions for beautiful Syrian regions as
well...
نكون معكم فيها ببرنامج جولات.
...so we can be with you there in the program "Jawlat"
(Tours).